I'm home!
ただいま:Here I am/I'm home!|presently
ただいま
Welcome back.
おかえり:return|welcome home
おかえり
How's Dad?
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 具合[ぐあい]:condition/state/manner
父さんの具合どう？
腰[こし, コシ]:back/lower back|body (of hair, noodle, paper, etc.), 腰[ごし]:posture/position/pose, ずいぶん:very/extremely|contemptible, 良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|
腰はずいぶん良くなったんだけどね
His back's a lot better now.
His blood pressure's running high though,
高血圧[こうけつあつ]:high blood pressure/hypertension, 気味[きみ, きび]:sensation/feeling|tendency, 気味[ぎみ]:-like/-looking/-looked
高血圧気味だから
ついで:next/secondly/subsequently, ついで:opportunity/occasion, 治す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||, もらえる:to be able to receive/to be able to take|could you (give me), 置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||
ついでに治してもらえって置いてきたわ
so I left him there to get
treated for that, too.
Here, a present.
お土産[おみやげ, おみあげ]:present/souvenir
これ　お土産
Oh, Hokunan lost?
負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||
あら　負けちゃったの？　北南
暑い[あつい]:hot (weather, etc.)/warm
甲子園　暑そうだなー
Sure looks hot at Koshien.
If Ezonoo had made it there,
エゾノーが行ってたら
私たち[わたしたち, わたくしたち]:we/us, 今ごろ[いまごろ]:about this time, スタンド:stands/bleachers
私たち今ごろあのスタンドにいたかもね
we might've been
in the stands about now.
積み出す[つみだす]:to send off, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
積み出し終わりました
All done with the stacking!
疲れ[つかれ]:tiredness/fatigue
おう　お疲れさん
Thanks, good job!
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
頑張ってるみたいね
Hard at work, I see.
おかえりなさい:welcome home
あっ　おかえりなさい
Oh, welcome back.
Ah.
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), すっかり:all/completely/totally, 農家[のうか]:farmer/farming family|farmhouse
２週間ですっかり農家の男になってきたんじゃないの
You've turned into quite the farmer
over the past two weeks, no?
Thanks...
どうも…
Don't worry.
大丈夫よ
父ちゃん[とうちゃん, とっちゃん]:dad/daddy/papa, 置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||
父ちゃんは置いてきたから
I left Pa at the hospital.
Oh, they lost...
負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||
あっ　負けちゃったんですね
Let's hope Ezonoo can
make it next year.
来年[らいねん]:next year, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|
来年はエゾノーが行けるといいわね
Do you think Icchan can
become a regular this fall?
秋[とき]:time|occasion|chance||, 秋[あき]:autumn/fall, レギュラー:regular
いっちゃん秋からレギュラーになれそう？
Hm, I'm not sure.
う～ん　分かんないけど
He said he can only go home
during the first week,
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, 初め[はじめ]:beginning|first (in line, etc.)|origin|, 初め[ぞめ]:first doing of ... (ever, in one's life, in the new year, etc.), 週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of)
家に帰れるのは初めの１週間だけで
後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|
後はほぼ休みなしだって
and after that there'll
be no real breaks.
そうだ　八軒君
Oh, Hachiken-kun.
You haven't had any breaks
since you came here, right?
お休み[おやすみ]:holiday|sleep|Good night, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
うちに来てからお休みもらってないっしょ
Why don't you go somewhere
for a breather?
息抜き[いきぬき]:taking a breather/relaxation/vent hole
息抜きにどっか行っといで
"Somewhere"?
どこかって…
Where?
どこへ？
あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
車出してあげるよ
I'll drive you.
Is there anywhere nearby
you want to go?
近場[ちかば]:nearby place
近場で行きたいとこないかい？
Um, is there anywhere nearby
you can go to have fun?
えーと:let me see/well/errr ..., 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places
えーと…この近くで遊べる所って？
Maybe the Ito-Yokado store?
イトーヨーカドーかな
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
ここから１００ｋｍくらいだし
It's only 100 kilometers
away from here, too!
Maybe an hour's drive?
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
車で１時間くらいかな
However, this experience has surely
strengthened the players.
Um...
えっと:let me see/well/errr ...
えっと…
選手[せんしゅ]:player (in game)/team member, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
…選手たちの強さにつながったはずです
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||, 投げる[なげる]:to throw/to cast away|to face defeat, 抜く[ぬく]:to extract|to do something to the end|to surpass||, 投手[とうしゅ]:pitcher, 年生[ねんせい]:pupil in ... year/student in ... year
９回を投げ抜いた日高投手もまだ２年生です
Higata pitched nine innings and is only a second year.
農場[のうじょう]:farm (agriculture), すげえ:incredible/unbelievable, でかい:huge/big/gargantuan, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
そういや　多摩子んちの農場すげえでかくて面白いから
Now that I think about it,
若い[わかい]:young|immature|low (number), チーム:team, 来年[らいねん]:next year, 甲子[きのえね, かっし]:first of the sexagenary cycle, 園[その, えん]:garden (esp. man-made)/orchard|place
若いチームで来年こそ　ここ　甲子園で…
It's a young team.
Komaba told me to check
out Tamako's family farm
Let's hope they will find redemption
next year here at the nationals.
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 駒場[こまば]:pasture used for grazing horses (esp. ponies)
一度見てこいって駒場が言ってたな
because it's super huge
and really interesting.
本格的[ほんかくてき]:genuine|full-scale|full-fledged, 夏[なつ]:summer, 夏[か]:Xia (dynasty of China; perhaps mythological), 日差し[ひざし]:sunlight/rays of the sun
本格的な夏の日差しが
肌[はだ, はだえ]:skin|body (in the context of intimate bodily contact)|surface|, 焦がす[こがす]:to burn/to scorch/to singe, 様[ざま]:mess|-ways|in the act of ...|, 様[さま]:Mr.|makes words more polite (usu. in fixed expressions)|state
肌を焦がしていく様に
恋焦がれる[こいこがれる]:to yearn for/to pine/to be deeply in love with
私もあなたに恋焦がれる
海[うみ, み]:sea/ocean/waters, ドライブ:drive/trip by car/driving, 運転[うんてん]:operation (of a machine, etc.)|driving|working (capital, etc.)
海へドライブ 運転するよ
横顔[よこがお]:face in profile/profile/face seen from the side, 撫でる[なでる]:to stroke/to caress|to comb (hair), 潮風[しおかぜ]:salty sea breeze/salt wind, 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
横顔撫でる 潮風が気持ちいいsummer day
la la la summer day
ビーチパラソル:beach parasol/beach umbrella, カラフル:colorful/colourful
ビーチパラソルカラフルだ yeah
砂浜[すなはま]:sandy beach, 咲く[さく]:to bloom, 花[はな]:flower|cherry blossom|beauty||, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
砂浜に咲く　花みたい
KISS YOU あなたの心
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
もっともっと近くにいたい　感じたい
私だけ見て
膨らむ[ふくらむ]:to expand/to swell (out)/to get big
KISS YOU ぐっと膨らんだ
胸[むね, むな]:chest|breasts|heart||, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, 唇[くちびる]:lips, のせる:to place on (something)|to give (someone) a ride/to give a lift, 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
胸の思い　唇にのせて　伝えたいと
だから　KISS YOU
だから　さあ　KISS YOU
Episode 7
Hachiken
Goes to Giga Farm
Oh, this is it!
あっ　ここ　ここ
Everything from here on
is part of the Giga Farm.
先[さき]:previous|point (e.g. pencil)|head (of a line)||, 先[せん]:former/previous|first move (in go, shogi, etc.), 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole
ここから先全部ＧＩＧＡ　ＦＡＲＭさんだよ
広っ！
Vast!
でかっ！
Huge!
多[た]:multi-
多っ！
So many!
Hello.
こんにちは:hello/good day (daytime greeting)
こんにちは
Tama—
多摩…！？
Are you Tamako's friends
who wanted to visit?
見学[けんがく]:inspection/study by observation/field trip, 希望[きぼう]:hope/wish/aspiration, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
見学希望の多摩子のお友達かね？
お邪魔[おじゃま]:hindrance/intrusion
お邪魔します　八軒勇吾です
Thank you for having us.
I'm Hachiken Yuugo.
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead
御影アキです
I'm Mikage Aki.
I'm Aki's mother.
母[はは, はわ]:mother
アキの母です
Nice to meet you all.
どうも　多摩子の父です
I'm Tamako's father.
ゆっくり:slowly/at ease/restful, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ゆっくり見ていってください
Please take your time.
Their DNA's working way overtime.
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place, 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
頑張り過ぎだろ　ＤＮＡ！
Tamako, your friends are here.
友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
多摩子　お友達来たぞ
携帯[けいたい, ケイタイ]:something carried (in the hand)/handheld|mobile telephone
携帯！？
A cell phone?!
Yup, okay. Hurry up.
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
うん　分かった　早くな
How big is this place?
広い[ひろい]:spacious/vast/wide
どんだけ広いんだよ
Oh, I guess I can get a signal here.
つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
あっ　ここ　つながるんだ
0001  Equestrian Club
0002  Mom
0003  Mom
0004  Tokiwa
0005  Mom
0006  Mom
0007  Ookawa-Senpai
0008  Mom
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), メール:email
うわ　２週間分のメールが
Wow, two weeks' worth of texts.
0002  Mom
0003  Mom
0004  Tokiwa
0005  Mom
0006  Mom
0007  Ookawa-Senpai
0008  Mom
0009  Mom
0003  Mom
0004  Tokiwa
0005  Mom
0006  Mom
0007  Ookawa-Senpai
0008  Mom
0009  Mom
0010  Mom
0004  Tokiwa
0005  Mom
0006  Mom
0007  Ookawa-Senpai
0008  Mom
0009  Mom
0010  Mom
0011  Mom
多摩子もうすぐ来るから　ちょっと待っててな
Tamako will be here in a bit,
so please be patient.
Oh, sure!
あっ　はい
全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 乳牛[ちちうし, にゅうぎゅう]:milk cow/dairy cattle/milch cow, 頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 軒[のき]:eaves|narrow aisle surrounding the core of a temple building, 軒[けん]:counter for buildings (esp. houses)|suffix for a pen name, stage name, etc., 農家[のうか]:farmer/farming family|farmhouse, 従業員[じゅうぎょういん]:employee/worker
全部で乳牛８００頭　４軒の農家と従業員…
We have 800 dairy cows,
four farm houses and the employees.
Wow.
バカでかい:enormous/gargantuan/immense, 手入れ[ていれ]:care/looking after|(police) raid, 行き届く[いきとどく, ゆきとどく]:to be scrupulous/to be attentive/to be prudent
バカでかいけど　手入れが行き届いてるなぁ
Even though it's huge,
it's well-maintained.
Whoa!
何やってんのよ　八軒
What do you think you're
doing, Hachiken?
What was that for, Tamako?
何すんだよ　多摩子…
Only staff
allowed
in order
to prevent
epidemics.
If you're going to take a
look, disinfect your shoes!
見学[けんがく]:inspection/study by observation/field trip, 靴[くつ]:shoes/boots/footwear, 消毒[しょうどく]:disinfection/sterilization/sterilisation, 伝染病[でんせんびょう]:infectious disease/contagious disease/epidemic, 予防[よぼう]:prevention/precaution/protection against
見学するなら　靴を消毒　伝染病予防
Disinfectant
Prevent epidemics!
It's common sense!
常識[じょうしき]:common sense/good sense/common knowledge
常識でしょ！
あー　はいはい
Oh, fine, fine.
伝染病[でんせんびょう]:infectious disease/contagious disease/epidemic, 処分[しょぶん]:disposal|punishment|putting down (e.g. diseased animal)
伝染病によっては全頭処分なのよ
Depending on the disease,
we'd have to get rid of all of them!
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||
牛８００頭殺して
If you're willing to
accept the consequences
経営[けいえい]:management/administration/operation, 陣[じん]:battle formation|camp|group|, 軒[のき]:eaves|narrow aisle surrounding the core of a temple building, 軒[けん]:counter for buildings (esp. houses)|suffix for a pen name, stage name, etc., 従業員[じゅうぎょういん]:employee/worker, 路頭[ろとう]:roadside/wayside, 迷わす[まよわす]:to puzzle/perplex/bewilder, 覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
経営陣４軒と従業員を路頭に迷わす覚悟があるっていうなら
for killing 800 cows and
leaving the management
and workforce of four farms
jobless and out on the streets,
ずかずか:making a rude entrance/barging in
ずかずか入ってもいいのよ
by all means, stomp right in.
I am so sorry!
申し訳[もうしわけ]:apology/excuse
申し訳ありません！
What the hell is this?
何じゃこりゃー！　でかー！
It's humongous!
It's a milking unit called
a rotary parlor.
ロータリー:rotary/roundabout/traffic circle, パーラー:parlor/parlour, 搾乳[さくにゅう]:milking (a cow), 設備[せつび]:equipment/device/facilities
ロータリーパーラーっていう搾乳設備よ
すげえ:incredible/unbelievable
すげえ！
It's amazing...
Up to 40 cows can be on it
at the same time.
一度[いちど, ひとたび]:once|temporarily|one degree, 頭[とう]:counter for large animals (e.g. head of cattle), 頭[あたま, かしら]:head|hair (on one's head)|mind||, 載る[のる]:to be placed on/to be set on|to appear (in print)
一度に４０頭載れるわ
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), メリーゴーラウンド:merry-go-round
牛のメリーゴーラウンド
It's like a cow merry-go-round...
作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 動き回る[うごきまわる]:to move around, 済む[すむ]:to finish|to merely result in something less severe than expected|to feel at ease|
作業するのに動き回らなくて済むし
Workers don't have to
move around,
流れ作業[ながれさぎょう]:assembly-line system, 効率[こうりつ]:efficiency/efficacy/performance, スピーディー:speedy, 搾る[しぼる]:to wring (towel, rag)|to squeeze (fruit to extract juice)|to rack (one's brains)||, ことができる:can (do)/to be able to (do)/can be done
流れ作業で効率よくスピーディーに搾ることができるの
so milking is done in a speedy
and efficient assembly line.
At my place, we'd be done milking
in one and a half turns!
回転[かいてん]:rotation (usu. around something)/revolution/turning, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 搾る[しぼる]:to wring (towel, rag)|to squeeze (fruit to extract juice)|to rack (one's brains)||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
うちだったら　これ１回転半で搾り終わっちゃう
そうだな
Yeah.
Huh?
あれ？
Is that cow being moved somewhere?
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
あの牛　どっか連れてくのか？
処分[しょぶん]:disposal|punishment|putting down (e.g. diseased animal)
処分するのよ
We're getting rid of it.
It hurt its leg.
足[あし]:foot|leg|gait||, 足[そく]:counter for pairs (of socks, shoes, etc.)
足をケガしてるの
治す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||
でも　そんなの治してやれば
But you could just treat it...
治療費[ちりょうひ]:doctor's fee (bill), 掛かる[かかる]:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang|to come into view||
治療費掛かるじゃない
That'd cost money.
Until it gets better,
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 餌[えさ, え]:(animal) feed/fodder|bait, 食い込み[くいこみ]:wedgie (to a girl) i.e. pulling up the underwear from the back, driving it into the vulva, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 搾乳[さくにゅう]:milking (a cow), 量[りょう]:quantity/amount/volume, 量[はか]:progress, 減る[へる]:to decrease (in size or number)/to diminish/to abate
その間　餌の食い込みも悪くなって搾乳量も減るし
it won't eat as much
and it'll produce less milk, too.
That's cold.
冷[れい]:cold/cool|cold sake, 冷[ひや]:cold water|cold sake|cold
冷てえ
何言ってるの
What're you talking about?
We aren't running a charity here.
慈善事業[じぜんじぎょう]:philanthropic work/charitable enterprise
慈善事業じゃないのよ
効率[こうりつ]:efficiency/efficacy/performance, 大量[たいりょう]:large quantity/massive (quantity)/mass (e.g. mass production, mass transit, mass destruction), 生産[せいさん]:production/manufacture, 生産[せいざん]:live birth, ことによる:depending on the circumstances|due to (with modifying verb)
効率よく大量に生産することによって
By being efficient
with mass production,
収入[しゅうにゅう]:income/receipts/revenue, 安定[あんてい]:stability/steadiness/equilibrium
収入が安定するし
we stabilize our revenue.
And because it's a partnership,
共同[きょうどう]:doing together (as equals)/sharing/common (land, etc.), 経営[けいえい]:management/administration/operation, ローテーション:rotation, 休み[やすみ]:rest|vacation|dormancy (of a silkworm prior to moulting), 取れる[とれる]:to come off|(of pain, a fever, etc.) to disappear|to be caught||
共同経営だからこそ　ローテーションで休みを取れる
the workers can rotate and take breaks.
Farms using the antiquated, unprofitable
and back-breaking business model
もうかる:to be profitable/to yield a profit, きつい:intense/severe|determined, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
もうからない　きついなんて
時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 農業[のうぎょう]:agriculture, 世の中[よのなか]:society/the world/the times, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.), いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good
前時代の農業じゃ　今の世の中戦っていけないわよ
can't compete in this day and age.
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
多摩ちゃんはすごいね
You're amazing, Tama-chan.
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
しっかり考えてて
You've thought this through.
能天気[のうてんき, ノーてんき]:optimistic/thoughtless/carefree
あなたたちが能天気なだけじゃなくって
Maybe you're all just
too happy-go-lucky.
経営者[けいえいしゃ]:manager/proprietor, 志望[しぼう]:wish/desire/ambition, きっちり:exactly/precisely|closely, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, なさる:to do
経営者志望なら　きっちり考えなさいよ
If you intend to manage a farm,
you should think things through.
後継ぎ[あとつぎ]:heir/successor, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 婿[むこ]:husband/groom|(one's) son-in-law
アキちゃん後継ぎなんだから早いとこいい婿さんつかまえとかんと
Aki-chan, you're the heir!
You have to catch a good husband, stat!
大丈夫だぁ
It's fine!
しっかり者[しっかりもの]:person of firm character/stable person/gutsy person, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, 牧場[ぼくじょう, まきば]:farm (livestock)/ranch (US)|pasture land, 任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
アキはしっかり者だから　安心して牧場任せられるわ
Aki's got a good head
on her shoulders,
so we can safely leave
the ranch to her.
It's not like it's normal
高[たか, だか]:quantity/amount/volume, 高[こう]:high school|high-, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||, 特殊[とくしゅ]:special/particular/peculiar
高１でそんなことまで考えてる方が特殊だろ
for a first-year high school
student to think about that.
Hachiken, you seem like you're
strong in Math and English,
英[はなぶさ, かぼう]:calyx/corolla, 英[えい]:Britain/British, 数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount
八軒　あなた英·数と強そうだから
卒業[そつぎょう]:graduation/completion (e.g. of a course)|outgrowing something, 就職[しゅうしょく]:finding employment/getting a job, なさる:to do
卒業したらここに就職しなさいよ
so you should come work
here when you graduate.
経営[けいえい]:management/administration/operation, 部門[ぶもん]:division (of a larger group)/branch/field, 海外[かいがい]:foreign/abroad/overseas, 販売[はんばい, ハンバイ]:sales/selling/marketing, スキル:skill, 生かす[いかす]:to make (the best) use of|to let live|to revive, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
経営部門や海外販売部門でスキルを生かしてあげるわよ
I'll let you exercise your
skills in our management
or international sales department.
Don't just decide my future for me!
将来[しょうらい]:future (usually near)/prospects, 勝手[かって]:one's own convenience|surroundings|convenience||, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
人の将来まで勝手に決めんな
Are you finished looking around?
見学[けんがく]:inspection/study by observation/field trip, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
見学終わった？
Oh, hello—
あっ　どうも…
姉ちゃん[ねえちゃん]:elder sister/girl
姉ちゃんいたのか
She has an older sister?
お構い[おかまい]:entertainment/hospitality|banishment (Edo period), なさる:to do
何もお構いできなくてごめんなさいね
I'm sorry I couldn't come by earlier.
Oh, not at all!
とんでも:unthinkable/unexpected/outrageous
いえいえ　とんでもない
娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman), お世話になる[おせわになる]:to receive favor (favour)/to be much obliged to someone/to be indebted
いつも娘がお世話になっております
Thank you for looking
after my daughter.
おかん！？
It's her mom?!
Scary...
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid, 稲田[いなだ]:paddy field/rice field, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family
怖い…　稲田家　怖い…！
The Inada family is really scary...
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 案内[あんない]:information/guidance|to guide, 差し上げる[さしあげる]:to give/to offer|to lift up
多摩子　ちゃんと案内して差し上げたの？
Tamako, did you give
them a proper tour?
You didn't even get them
anything to drink.
飲み物[のみもの]:drink/beverage
飲み物もお出ししないで
なさる:to do
あら　ごめんなさい
Oh, sorry.
Please wait here.
ちょっと待ってて
I apologize.
なさる:to do, 気が利く[きがきく]:to be sensible/to be smart|to be thoughtful
ごめんなさいね　気が利かなくて
She's not very considerate.
Oh, not at all.
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), 娘[じょう]:unmarried woman|Miss|-ess, 娘[むすめ]:(my) daughter|girl (i.e. a young, unmarried woman)
いえいえ　あの…　しっかりした娘さんで
Um, she's very down-to-earth.
Is she?
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built), かしら:I wonder, かしら:head|hair (on one's head)
しっかりかしら
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 経営[けいえい]:management/administration/operation, 心構え[こころがまえ]:preparedness/readiness/mental attitude, 聞かす[きかす]:to inform about/to read to/to sing for
あぁ　さっき経営の心構えとか聞かされて
Um, she was telling us about things
like the management mindset earlier.
う～ん　何かねぇ
Hmm, well...
後を継ぐ[あとをつぐ]:to succeed (someone)/to take over from/to pick up the torch, 気[き]:spirit|nature|motivation||, 気[げ]:seeming/giving the appearance of/giving one the feeling of, うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
後を継ぐ気でいてくれるのはうれしいんだけどねぇ
It's great that she wants to carry
on the family business, but...
I worry that she's
choosing her path because
農家[のうか]:farmer/farming family|farmhouse, 継ぐ[つぐ]:to succeed (someone in a business or inheritance), 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
農家の子だから自分が継がなきゃって理由で
進路[しんろ]:route/course|one's future course (e.g. after graduating high school), 選ぶ[えらぶ]:to choose/to select, じゃう:to do something completely, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
進路を選んじゃってるんじゃないかって心配で…
she feels obligated
by being in a farming family.
Have some tea.
茶[ちゃ]:tea|tea plant (Camellia sinensis)|tea preparation||, どうぞ:please/kindly|by all means
お茶　どうぞ
Oh, thanks, Tama-chan.
ありがと:Thank you
あっ　ありがと　多摩ちゃん
Well? What were you guys talking about?
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
何？　何の話してたの？
Your mom and I worry that you
might be restricting yourself
後継ぎ[あとつぎ]:heir/successor, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, 縛る[しばる]:to tie/to bind
多摩子が後継ぎって言葉に縛られてるんじゃないかって
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
父さんたち心配してるんだ
by focusing too much
on being the heir.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, ふらふら:unsteady (e.g. on one's feet)/staggering|wandering, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
もっとふらふら考えていいのよ
You can still explore other options, you know.
The heir?
後継ぎ[あとつぎ]:heir/successor
後継ぎ？
勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
何か勘違いしてるみたいだから言っておくけど
I think you've got me wrong,
so let me say something.
I love money!
お金[おかね]:money, 大好き[だいすき]:loveable/very likeable/like very much
私はお金が大好きです！
合理的[ごうりてき]:rational/reasonable/logical, スピーディー:speedy, スマート:smart/stylish
合理的に！　スピーディーに！　スマートに！
To generate high revenue
through logical, speedy,
smart practices is to experience
indescribable satisfaction!
高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 収益[しゅうえき]:earnings/proceeds/returns, 充実[じゅうじつ]:fullness|enhancement|replenishment, 感ずる[かんずる]:to feel/to sense
高い収益を出すことにえも言われぬ充実を感じます！
農業[のうぎょう]:agriculture, 戦国[せんごく]:belligerent country/country in civil war/warring states, 時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|
今や農業戦国時代
It's now the Warring States
Period for agriculture.
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 戦う[たたかう]:to make war (on)|to compete (against)|to struggle (against adversities, etc.)
世界と戦うには
Mom and Dad, your loose
management practices
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, 経営[けいえい]:management/administration/operation, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner, まだまだ:still some way to go before the goal/still more to come/much more, 隙[すき, げき]:gap|break|chink (in one's armor, armour)|
父さんたちの経営方法ではまだまだ隙があるわ
still aren't enough for us
to take on the world!
就職[しゅうしょく]:finding employment/getting a job, 経営[けいえい]:management/administration/operation, 口出し[くちだし]:interference/meddling/butting in
私がここに就職したいのは　経営に口出ししたいから
The reason why I want to work here
is because I want to have
a say in the business!
Once I join the company,
入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company, お払い箱[おはらいばこ]:discarding/firing (an employee)
私が入社したら父さんはお払い箱よ
you're going out the door, Dad!
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 下克上[げこくじょう]:juniors dominating seniors/retainer supplanting his lord, 発言[はつげん]:statement/remark/observation
何！？　まさかの下克上発言！？
What?!
Don't tell me you're
announcing a coup?!
So you were thinking overthrowing us
instead of succeeding us!
後継ぎ[あとつぎ]:heir/successor, 乗っ取り[のっとり]:capture/takeover/hijack, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
後継ぎではなく乗っ取りを考えているなんて！
恐ろしい[おそろしい]:terrible/dreadful|surprising
多摩子…恐ろしい子！
Tamako, what a fearsome child!
つぶす:to smash/to crush|to shut down
今のうちにつぶしておかねば！
We must crush you while we still can...
ごらん:(please) try to|(please) look, なさる:to do
オホホホホホ！　できるものならやってごらんなさい
Give it your best shot!
What a down-to-earth girl...
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built)
しっかりした子だねぇ
Tamako's unshakable...
She's something else.
揺るぐ[ゆるぐ]:to shake/to waver/to tremble, パネェ:a lot/to a very great extent/absolutely
揺るがねえ　多摩子　パネェ
Tamako's really firm in
her own convictions.
多摩子のやつ　ホントブレないなぁ
I'm sure parents feel secure
when they have an heir like her.
後継者[こうけいしゃ]:successor, 親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 御[ご]:honorific/polite|honorific suffix, 御[ぎょ]:honorific affix|honorific prefix, 安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice
ああいう後継者がいれば　親御さんも安心するんだろうなぁ
寝首[ねくび]:head of a sleeping person, かかれる:to span/to bridge/to cross, かかれる:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang
いや　寝首かかれるだろ
Nah, they might get
killed in their sleep.
Um, Mikage...
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead
あのさ　御影
Are you worried about carrying
on your family business?
家を継ぐ[いえをつぐ]:to succeed to a house, 悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled
家を継ぐことで何か悩んでるのか？
U-Um, if that's not it, sorry.
勘違い[かんちがい]:misunderstanding/wrong guess
あぁ…　いや　勘違いだったらごめんな
何かさ…えっと…
It's just that... well...
相談に乗る[そうだんにのる]:to give advice/to counsel/to take part in a consultation
そうだ　俺でよかったら相談に乗るよ
Oh! If you want to talk, I'm here.
Er...
…って　アホか　俺！
You idiot!
進学[しんがく]:entering a higher-level school, esp. going on to university, コース:course (route, trail, course of study, course of action, plan, option), 逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away, ふらふら:unsteady (e.g. on one's feet)/staggering|wandering
進学コースから逃げてきてふらふらしてるやつが
You ran away from the
prep school route!
進路[しんろ]:route/course|one's future course (e.g. after graduating high school), 相談に乗る[そうだんにのる]:to give advice/to counsel/to take part in a consultation
人の進路相談に乗るとか　何言ってんだー！
How can an aimless guy like you give
anyone advice about their future?!
ありがと:Thank you
ありがとね
Thanks.
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, うれしい:happy/glad/pleasant
気持ち　うれしいよ
I appreciate the thought.
Mikage...
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead
御影ぇぇ…
Why are you crying, Hachiken-kun?
泣く[なく]:to cry/to weep/to sob
何で八軒君が泣いてるの？
You know, you're kind of like a horse.
馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
八軒君ってさ　馬みたいだよね
馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop
馬？
A horse?
Oh, look!
あっ　見て　見て
すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength), 大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, バンカー:banker, サイロ:silo
すごい大きなバンカーサイロ
It's a giant bunker silo!
What is it?
どうしたの？
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead, 馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
御影に俺って馬みたいだって
Mikage said I'm like a horse.
I wonder what she means.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
どういう意味だ？
馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop
馬？
A horse?
Timid?
臆病者[おくびょうもの]:coward
臆病者？
良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|, 労働力[ろうどうりょく]:labor/labour/manpower
良い労働力？
Good labor?
Horse sashimi?
馬刺し[ばさし]:horse-meat sashimi
馬刺し？
Oh, yum.
不細工[ぶさいく, ブサイク]:clumsy (work)|plain (e.g. looks)/ugly
不細工！？
Ugly?!
不細工[ぶさいく, ブサイク]:clumsy (work)|plain (e.g. looks)/ugly
不細工…不細工って言いたいの！？
Ugly?
Maybe she means I'm ugly?!
Hello? Yes.
はい　うん
分かった　すぐ行く
All right. I'll be right there.
ばたばた:flapping/rattling (sound)|commotion
ばたばたしてすみませんね
Sorry things are so hectic.
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 出産[しゅっさん]:childbirth/(giving) birth|production (of goods), 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from), みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
牛の出産が始まったみたいで
It seems a cow is calving.
Oh, why don't you go watch,
Hachiken-kun?
見学[けんがく]:inspection/study by observation/field trip, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
あら　見学させてもらったら　八軒君
Have you ever seen one?
見たことある？
No...
いや…
I'm sure you'll be awed.
きっと:surely/undoubtedly|sternly, 感動[かんどう]:being deeply moved emotionally/excitement/passion
きっと感動するわよ
Hm, I wonder.
どうかな
Huh?
えっ？　何？　何これ！
What?
What's this?
What're you having me do?
俺　何やらされてんの？
It's a breech birth.
逆子[さかご]:breech presentation (feet or buttocks-first birth)/breech delivery/breech birth
逆子だ
We'll pull it right out in tandem
with the cow when she strains.
親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 息[いき, おき]:breath/breathing|tone, 息[むすこ, そく]:son|penis, 合わせる[あわせる]:to match (rhythm, speed, etc.)|to join together|to face||, 一気[いっき]:chug!/drink! (said repeatedly as a party cheer), 引っ張る[ひっぱる]:to pull|to string (lines)|to pull towards oneself (e.g. someone's sleeve)||
親牛の息みに合わせて一気に引っ張り出す
It's a big one,
大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, こっこ:national treasury
大きいこっこだから
みぞおち:pit of the stomach/solar plexus|place where water falls, 肩[かた]:shoulder, 詰まる[つまる]:to be packed (with)|to be blocked (road, pipe, etc.)|to shorten (width, interval, etc.)||, アウト:out
みぞおちや肩で詰まったらアウトだぞ
so if it gets stuck at the stomach
or the shoulder, it's a goner.
うーっす！
Okay!
よし　引けー！
Okay, pull!
Yeah!
One more time!
回[かい]:counter for occurrences|a time|inning (baseball)||
もう１回！　引けー！
Pull!
Let's land it with the next one!
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
さあ　次で決めるぞ！
引けー！
Pull!
This is bad...
まずい:poor-quality/shoddy|unskillful, まずい:unappetising/unappetizing|unskillful, 息をする[いきをする]:to breathe
まずいな　息をしてない
It's not breathing.
Hup!
しっかり:tightly (holding on)/firmly|strongly (built)
ほれ！　しっかりしろ！
C'mon, get it together!
There, there, there, there!
Mouth-to-mouth!
人工[じんこう]:artificial/man-made/human work, 呼吸[こきゅう]:breathing|knack|harmony|
人工呼吸！
Yeah!
おー！
よかったー
Thank goodness!
What do you think, Hachiken-kun?
どう？　八軒君
生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 誕生[たんじょう]:birth/creation/formation, 素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent
生命の誕生って素晴らしいっしょ？
Isn't the birth of a life amazing?
It's gross.
グロい:grotesque/disgusting/gross
グロい…
Wouldn't one normally
say they were moved?
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 感動[かんどう]:being deeply moved emotionally/excitement/passion
普通ここは「感動した」では？
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||
無理　無理　無理　無理！
No freakin' way!
No, no!
グロい:grotesque/disgusting/gross, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
ない　ない！　グロい！　怖い！
It's gross! Scary!
生命[せいめい]:life/existence, 誕生[たんじょう]:birth/creation/formation
生命の誕生よ
It's the birth of a life!
感動[かんどう]:being deeply moved emotionally/excitement/passion, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
感動しないなんてあなたおかしいんじゃないの！？
How can you not be moved by it?
Is something wrong with you?
That's just the arrogance
of a cattle farmer!
畜産[ちくさん]:animal husbandry, 農家[のうか]:farmer/farming family|farmhouse, 傲慢[ごうまん]:haughty/arrogant/insolent
それは畜産農家の傲慢だぁ
感動[かんどう]:being deeply moved emotionally/excitement/passion, 押し付ける[おしつける]:to press/to push/to force
感動とか押し付けんなー
Don't push your views on me!
Hup.
連れる[つれる]:to lead/to take (a person)
どこに連れてくんだ？
Where are they taking it?
To a shed for calves.
子牛[こうし, こうじ]:calf/small cow, 専用[せんよう]:exclusive use/personal use|private (e.g. network), 小屋[こや, しょうおく]:hut|small theatre (theater)|one's own house
子牛専用の小屋よ
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
母牛と一緒じゃないのか
They don't keep them with the moms?
管理[かんり]:control/management (e.g. of a business), やすい:cheap/inexpensive|calm, やすい:easy|likely to .../have a tendency to ...
管理しやすいように
We separate them right away to
make them easier to manage.
生まれる[うまれる]:to be born, 親子[おやこ, しんし]:parent and child, 別々[べつべつ]:separately/individually
生まれてすぐ親子別々にされるのよ
えっ？
What?!
テレビ:television/TV, 牧歌的[ぼっかてき]:pastoral/idyllic
じゃあ　テレビで見るような牧歌的なやつは…
Then... the kind of pastoral
ideal you see on TV...
Doesn't exist.
ないわね
うちもないなー
It doesn't happen at our place, either.
To be separated right at
birth is way too sad—
生まれる[うまれる]:to be born, 離れ離れ[はなればなれ]:separate/scattered/apart, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, かわいそう:poor/pitiable/pathetic
生まれてすぐ離れ離れなんてかわいそうじゃ…
顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
…って　おい　知らん顔かよ
Hey, wait! You don't even care?!
他人[たにん, ひと]:another person|unrelated person (i.e. not related by blood)|outsider, どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, 家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, 希薄[きはく]:thin (e.g. air)/diluted|lacking (e.g. empathy), 現代[げんだい]:nowadays/modern era/modern times
他人どころか家族の関係すらも希薄になりつつある現代に
In these modern times, when connections
among not only strangers
but also family members,
have grown increasingly tenuous,
せめて:at least/at most, せめて:offense/offence/method of attack, 動物界[どうぶつかい]:animal kingdom/Animalia, まとも:the front|honesty/uprightness, 親子関係[おやこかんけい]:parent-child relationship, 築く[きずく]:to build/to construct|to amass (e.g. fortune), 信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
せめて動物界だけはまともな親子関係が築けていると信じていたのに
I had hoped that the decency
of parent-child relationships
had at least been preserved
in the animal kingdom....
but you guys have—
お前らときたら…
なさる:to do
ちょっとどきなさい
Hey, get out of the way.
What're you doing?
何してんだ？
I'm giving the calf its first milk.
初乳[しょにゅう]:colostrum/foremilk/first milk, あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair)
初乳をあの子にあげるの
成長[せいちょう]:growth/grow to adulthood, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity, 成分[せいぶん]:ingredient/component/composition, たっぷり:full/in plenty/ample
成長に必要な成分がたっぷり入ってるのよ
This has a lot of things it needs
to grow strong and healthy.
I see.
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 乳[ちち, ち]:milk|breast|loop|
そっか　牛が乳を出すのは人間のためじゃなくて
Cows don't produce milk for humans,
but for their offspring, I guess.
子供[こども]:child/children, 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
自分の子供に飲ませるためなんだよな
いまさら:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh
いまさら何言ってるの
That should be obvious.
And we ask them to share some with us—
that's the dairy business.
乳[ちち, ち]:milk|breast|loop|, 分ける[わける]:to divide (into)|to share|to distinguish||, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, 酪農[らくのう]:dairy (farm)
その乳を分けてもらうのが酪農じゃない
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway
そこはいっちゃんとこもうちもみんな同じだよね
It's the same for us and
Icchan's place, too.
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born, 分ける[わける]:to divide (into)|to share|to distinguish||
そういえば　豚丼も生まれてすぐに分けられてたな
Come to think of it,
Pork Bowl was separated
soon after birth, too.
Um...
あの…
俺　やってみていい？
Can I try?
Here!
たくさん:a lot/lots|enough, 飲める[のめる]:to be able to drink|to be worth drinking
ほら　たくさん飲めよ
Drink up!
あれ？　どうしたんだよ？
Huh? What's the matter?
Here.
ほら
Give it to me.
貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out, ごらん:(please) try to|(please) look, なさる:to do
貸してごらんなさい
H-Hey, wait!
ちょ…ちょっと待てよ
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first
最初はこうやるの
The first time, you have
to do it this way.
ミルク:milk
これがミルクだって分かんないんだから
It doesn't know that this is milk.
何よ？
What?
There, you can take over now.
ほら　もう　大丈夫よ
O-Okay.
お…おう
This one's male,
雄[おす, オス]:male (animal), 雄[お]:male/man|husband
この子は雄だし
so in a week it'll get bought by a
beef cattle ranch—that's its fate.
週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), 肉牛[にくぎゅう]:beef cattle, 育成[いくせい]:rearing/training/nurture, 業[ごう]:karma (i.e. actions committed in a former life), 業[わざ]:deed/act/work, 買う[かう]:to buy|to value|to stir, 運命[うんめい]:fate/destiny/lot
あと１週間もしたら肉牛育成業者に買われていく運命なの
So if it's clinging to its
mom when the time comes,
べったり:sticking/clinging|with a smack (e.g. sitting down)
だから母牛にべったりしたままだと
it'll just make the separation harder.
別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell, しんどい:tired/frazzled|tiresome
別れがしんどくなるしね
I see.
乳牛[ちちうし, にゅうぎゅう]:milk cow/dairy cattle/milch cow, 雄[おす, オス]:male (animal), 雄[お]:male/man|husband, 肉牛[にくぎゅう]:beef cattle
そっか　乳牛の雄って　みんな肉牛にされるのか
So male cows all become beef cattle...
種牛[たねうし]:(breeding) bull, かぎり:limit/limits|degree
種牛にならないかぎり　ほぼ肉用だね
Unless they become a stud,
it's basically a given.
去勢[きょせい]:castration/enervation, 肥え太る[こえふとる]:to grow fat, 肉[にく, しし]:flesh|meat|the physical body (as opposed to the spirit)||, 一生[いっしょう]:whole life/a lifetime|(the only, the greatest, etc.) of one's life, 終える[おえる]:to finish|to graduate
で　去勢されて肥え太らされて肉になって一生を終えるの
They are castrated and fattened up,
then end their lives by becoming meat.
I'm glad I wasn't born a cow...
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 生まれる[うまれる]:to be born
牛に生まれなくてよかった
親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 相手にする[あいてにする]:to keep company/to listen to/to associate with, 食肉[しょくにく]:meat (for consumption), 一直線[いっちょくせん]:straight line, 運命[うんめい]:fate/destiny/lot
親に相手にされてない上に食肉一直線な運命
Not only does it not know its parents,
it's headed for the slaughterhouse.
奇麗[きれい, キレイ]:pretty|clean|completely
なのに　何も知らない奇麗な目をしている
Yet it has such innocent,
beautiful eyes.
澄む[すむ]:to clear (e.g. weather)/to become transparent, 瞳[ひとみ]:pupil (of eye)|eye, 精いっぱい[せいいっぱい]:the best one can do/one's best effort|with all one's might, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 牛丼[ぎゅうどん]:rice covered with beef and vegetables
その澄んだ瞳のまま精いっぱい生きてくれよ　牛丼
I hope you a full life and never
lose those clear eyes, Beef Bowl.
付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
だから名前付けちゃ駄目だって
We told you, don't give them names.
We ended up staying a
long time, didn't we?
すっかり:all/completely/totally, 長居[ながい]:long visit/overstaying
すっかり長居しちゃったねぇ
見れる[みれる]:to be able to see
でもいいもの見れたっしょ
But you had a good experience, right?
ロータリー:rotary/roundabout/traffic circle, パーラー:parlor/parlour, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
あのロータリーパーラーはすごかったね
The rotary parlor was
really impressive.
さらに:furthermore/again/after all, 人件費[じんけんひ]:personnel expenses/labor cost|indirect labour costs, 掛かる[かかる]:to take (a resource, e.g. time or money)|to hang|to come into view||, ロボット:robot, 式[しき]:equation|ceremony|style|
さらに人件費の掛からないロボット式のもあるのよ
There are even ones that are fully
automated to cut down on labor costs.
Wow.
へえー
Part-time work at a friend's house,
would that be a farm?
Mom
If you're staying
with them,
I'd like to say hi.
N
No
No n
No ne
しなくていい
No need!
No nee
No need.
Sending
Sent
Tokiwa
No clue what
to do with math
homework<(^o^)>
Once school starts,
please teach me!!
Tokiwa
メール:email, 和む[なごむ]:to be softened/to calm down
今日はお前のメールが俺を和ませるぜ　常盤
Today, your text's making
me feel better, Tokiwa!
こら　いつもお前は
Hey!
You again.
Don't eat so fast!
がっつく:to be greedy/to devour greedily
そんなにがっつかないの
What's the matter?
どうしたの？
不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange
不思議だよなぁ
It's strange.
You keep farm animals at arm's length,
経済[けいざい]:economics/business/finance, 動物[どうぶつ]:animal, 突き放す[つきはなす]:to thrust away/to push aside|to refuse bluntly
経済動物って突き放すわりに
but the way you manage them changes
depending on how attached you are.
情[じょう]:feelings|compassion|passion|, 運営[うんえい]:management/administration/operation, 方法[ほうほう]:method/process/manner, 変わる[かわる]:to change|to move to|to be different
情で運営方法が変わるのって
駒場[こまば]:pasture used for grazing horses (esp. ponies), そっと:softly/gently|secretly, そっと:face of the earth, 牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 処分[しょぶん]:disposal|punishment|putting down (e.g. diseased animal)
駒場んちはちょっとやそっとじゃ牛を処分しない
At Komaba's place, they don't get rid
of cows unless there's a major problem.
In comparison, at Tamako's
place, they're ruthless.
片[かた]:one (of a pair)|incomplete|few||, 片[へん]:piece/chip/flake, 所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 容赦[ようしゃ]:pardon/forgiveness|leniency, 処分[しょぶん]:disposal|punishment|putting down (e.g. diseased animal)
片や多摩子ん所は容赦なく処分
But that doesn't mean Tamako's place
doesn't care about their cows.
所[ところ, とこ]:place|address|district||, 所[しょ]:counter for places, 愛情[あいじょう]:love/affection
じゃあ　その多摩子ん所が愛情ないかっていうと
とも言う[ともいう]:also called
そうとも言えないし…
豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables
豚丼のことでも
And there's Pork Bowl.
クラス:class, しんどい:tired/frazzled|tiresome, 豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||
クラスのやつらはしんどいから　豚に名前付けるなって言うけど
Some of our classmates said
not to name pigs because it makes it tough.
But Inada-senpai said that it's okay,
and that I should stay conflicted.
稲田[いなだ]:paddy field/rice field, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||, 悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled
稲田先輩は付けていい　悩めって言うし…
I don't know. This industry's harsh...
業界[ぎょうかい]:business world/business circles/(the) industry, シビア:severe/strict
何つーか　この業界ってシビアだけどさ
but it feels like it's telling
me there's no "right" answer.
答え[こたえ, いらえ]:answer/reply/response
答えは１つじゃなくてもいいんだって
気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
言ってくれてる気がする
Pedigree Certificate
Miss Sunday Shougakukan
Father: Weekly Sunday
Mother: Miss Big Comic
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), 付く[つく]:to be attached|to remain imprinted|to bear (fruit, interest, etc.)||, 付く[づく]:to become (a state, condition, etc.)
牛って　みんな名前が付いてるんですか？
Do the cows all have names?
Yeah.
まあな
Even if we name livestock,
we can still kill them,
付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||, 家畜[かちく]:domestic animals/livestock/cattle, 殺す[ころす]:to kill, ペット:pet, ペット:polyethylene terephthalate/PET, 嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant
名前付けても家畜は殺せて　ペットを殺すのは嫌なのって…
while we can't stand to kill pets.
違い[ちがい]:difference/discrepancy
その違いって何だろう？
What's the difference?
Is it how much we love them?
愛情[あいじょう]:love/affection, 差[さ]:difference/variation|difference, 差[さし, サシ]:between (e.g. two people)|hindrance|arrhythmic section of recitative in noh music||
愛情の差？
Nah, we love our farm animals, too!
家畜[かちく]:domestic animals/livestock/cattle, なまる:to speak with an accent/to be corrupted (of word)/to mispronounce, なまる:to become blunt/to grow dull|to become less capable, 愛情[あいじょう]:love/affection
いや　わしらは家畜になまら愛情あるよ
豚[ぶた, ブタ]:pig (Sus scrofa domesticus)|fat person, 豚[とん]:pig/pork, 飼う[かう]:to keep (a pet or other animal)/to raise/to have, 愛する[あいする]:to love, 自信[じしん]:self-confidence/confidence (in oneself)
豚飼っても八軒君より愛する自信あるから
I'm sure that if we had pigs,
I'd love them more than you do!
あっさり:easily/readily|lightly (seasoned food, applied make-up, etc.), 食う[くう]:to eat|to live|to bite||
そのわりにはあっさり食っちゃいますよね
Despite that,
you're totally fine eating them.
Of course!
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is
そりゃ　そうさ
It's the kind of love you give 'em
thinking, "grow up good and tasty."
おいしい:delicious/tasty|attractive, 育てる[そだてる]:to raise|to train|to promote the growth of, 注ぐ[そそぐ]:to pour (into)|to sprinkle on from above|to concentrate one's spirit (strength, attention) on|, 注ぐ[つぐ]:to pour (into a vessel)/to fill/to dish out food or drink, 愛情[あいじょう]:love/affection
おいしく育てよって注ぐ愛情だもの
立場[たちば]:standpoint/position/situation, それぞれ:each/respectively
立場それぞれ　人それぞれ
Different people, different views.
愛情[あいじょう]:love/affection, 色々[いろいろ]:various|various colors (colours), 形[かたち, よう]:form/shape|visage, 形[かた, がた]:shape|collateral|obverse of an old "zeni" coin
愛情には色々な形があるのだよ　八軒君
There are many different kinds
of love, Hachiken-kun.
あー　そうだね
Oh, yeah.
I think I get what he
meant by kinds of love...
愛情[あいじょう]:love/affection, 形[かたち, よう]:form/shape|visage, 形[かた, がた]:shape|collateral|obverse of an old "zeni" coin
愛情の形ってのは分かるかも
この子たちも
We're raising these foals to become heroes
on the Ban'ei racetrack, right?
競馬[けいば]:horse racing, 競馬[くらべうま]:traditional horse-racing/originally two horses head-to-head or ten at a time, esp. May 5th event at Kamigamo shrine, ヒーロー:hero, 育てる[そだてる]:to raise|to train|to promote the growth of
ばんえい競馬でヒーローになってほしくて育ててるわけでしょ？
Yeah.
うん
And after being careful
about their health
体調[たいちょう]:physical condition, 気を付け[きをつけ]:(Stand to) attention!, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
体調に気を付けて　期待して　かわいがって
and taking good care of them
with high expectations,
突然[とつぜん]:abrupt/sudden/unexpected, 肉[にく, しし]:flesh|meat|the physical body (as opposed to the spirit)||
それがある日突然お肉にしてって言われたら
it'd be depressing if we
were suddenly told to turn
them into meat, you know?
がっかり:feel disappointed/dejected/lose heart
がっかりだよね
肉[にく, しし]:flesh|meat|the physical body (as opposed to the spirit)||, 育てる[そだてる]:to raise|to train|to promote the growth of
この子お肉にするために育ててきたわけじゃないのにって
Because you hadn't raised
them to become horse meat.
気がする[きがする]:to have a certain mood or feeling/to have a hunch
何か　分かる気がする
So I kind of get it.
農家[のうか]:farmer/farming family|farmhouse, 親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
農家の親もそんな気持ちがあるんだろうなぁ
I guess parents in farm families
feel the same way...
えーと:let me see/well/errr ..., ホント:truth/reality/actuality, おせっかい:meddling/meddlesomeness|meddler, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
あのさ　えーと…　ホントこういうのおせっかいかもしれないけど
Um, uh...
Maybe this is crossing a line,
やっぱ:too/also|still, 家を継ぐ[いえをつぐ]:to succeed to a house, 親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), 遠慮[えんりょ]:reserve|declining|forethought, 悩む[なやむ]:to be worried/to be troubled
やっぱ　家を継ぐことで親に遠慮して悩んでることあるのか？
but is there something bothering you
about carrying on the family business
that you're not telling your parents?
To be honest, I actually
want to work with horses.
私　本当はね
馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 就く[つく]:to ascend (the throne)|to take (seat, position, course, office, etc.)|to start (on a journey)|
馬関係の仕事に就きたいんだ
Oh, but it's not that I
don't like dairy farming.
酪農[らくのう]:dairy (farm), 嫌い[きらい]:dislike|suspicion|distinction, 嫌い[ぎらい]:dislike/hatred/fear
あっ　でもね　酪農が嫌いってわけじゃないのよ
Cows are cute, too!
牛[うし, ぎゅう]:cattle (Bos taurus)|beef|Chinese "Ox" constellation (one of the 28 mansions), カワイイ:cute/adorable/charming
牛もカワイイし
Besides, I'm the only child,
一人っ子[ひとりっこ]:(an) only child
それにうちは一人っ子だから
後継[こうけい]:succession|successor, 後継[あとつぎ]:heir/successor, 家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, つぶす:to smash/to crush|to shut down, ことになる:it has been decided (so) that/it has been arranged (so) that|it is the result (of)
後継がないと家つぶすことになるし
so if I don't carry on,
the farm will go under.
I don't want to disappoint my family
when they have high expectations.
期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope, 家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, がっかり:feel disappointed/dejected/lose heart
期待してる家族をがっかりさせたくないしね
Maybe that's where we're alike, trying to
live up to our families' expectations.
家族[かぞく]:family/members of a family, 期待に応える[きたいにこたえる]:to live up to expectations/to meet expectations
家族の期待に応えなきゃっていうところは
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
八軒君と一緒かな
We're not.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
一緒じゃないよ
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead, 親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, 話せる[はなせる]:to be able to speak/to be able to talk|to be understanding
御影　俺に親ときちんと話せって言ったよな
Mikage, you told me to be
straight with my parents.
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead
そういう御影こそ
But aren't you the one who isn't
being straight with your own parents?
気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|, 親[おや]:parent|dealer (in cards, mahjong, etc.)|founder|, 親[しん]:intimacy|close relative|pro- (e.g. pro-American, pro-Japanese, etc.), きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly, 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
自分の気持ちを親にきちんと話してないんじゃないのか？
Look, you have nice,
fun people in your family.
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead, 面白い[おもしろい]:interesting|amusing|pleasant
ほら　御影んちはみんな面白くていい人で
So if you tell them about your
dream, they'll understand!
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
だから夢のことちゃんと話せば分かってくれるよ
大丈夫だよ
It'll be okay!
It's not like my family.
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
俺んちと一緒じゃないよ
一生懸命[いっしょうけんめい]:very hard/with utmost effort/with all one's might
何で人のことなのにそんな一生懸命なの？
Why are you trying so hard
when it's about someone else?
It's just that... I find it sad.
何か　やなんだよ
夢[ゆめ]:dream
だって　夢があるんだろ？
I mean, you have a dream, right?
中学[ちゅうがく]:middle school/junior high school, 目標[めじるし]:mark/sign/landmark, 目標[もくひょう]:mark/objective/target, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up, 夢[ゆめ]:dream
俺　中学で目標なくなって夢もないから
I lost sight of my goals in junior high.
I don't really have a dream,
so I envy people who do
and are fired up about it.
夢[ゆめ]:dream, きらきら:glittering/sparkling/glistening, 正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, ねたましい:jealous/envious
夢があってきらきらしてるやつが正直ねたましいよ
夢[ゆめ]:dream, かなえる:to grant (request, wish)/to answer (prayer)|to fulfill (conditions), しんどい:tired/frazzled|tiresome, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, ながら:while/during|while, 踏ん張る[ふんばる]:to brace one's legs/to straddle/to stand firm
でもさ　夢かなえるためにしんどい思いしながら踏ん張ってるやつが
When someone's enduring a lot to
make their dream come true...
夢[ゆめ]:dream, かなう:to come true (wish)|to be suited
そういうやつの夢がかなわないのはやだよ
It's just sad if it doesn't come true!
Besides, when you're on a horse,
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead, 馬に乗る[うまにのる]:to get on a horse/to mount a horse
それに　御影が馬に乗ってるとき
真剣[しんけん]:seriousness/earnestness|real sword (as opposed to unsharpened or wooden practice weapon), カッコ:parentheses/brackets, カッコ:shape/form/figure, 良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|
真剣でカッコ良かったし
you're so cool and focused.
I kind of joined the equestrian
club because I saw you like that.
馬術[ばじゅつ]:horse-riding/horsemanship/equestrian art, 部分[ぶぶん]:portion/section/part
それ見て馬術部入った部分もあるし
And, well...
その…何つーか…
Whoa!
痛[いた]:ouch/ow/that hurt, 痛[つう]:pain/ache/-algia
あー　痛っ！
What, don't interrupt me!
邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
何だよ　邪魔すんなよ
Hachiken-kun, you're too nice.
痛い[いたい]:painful/sore|exceeding
痛ててっ！
八軒君ってさ
手いっぱい[ていっぱい]:having one's hands full/not having any room to do more/at the limit
自分のことで手いっぱいなのに
You take on other people's problems
even though you have enough of your own.
他人[たにん, ひと]:another person|unrelated person (i.e. not related by blood)|outsider, 抱え込む[かかえこむ]:to hold a thing in one's arms/to carry in one's arms|to take upon oneself, じゃう:to do something completely
他人のことを抱え込んじゃうお人よしだよね
What?
えっ？　何だよ
Man... Are you saying I'm
the type to lose out?
損する[そんする]:to lose (money, etc.)|to have wasted one's (time, etc.)/to have one's efforts come to naught, タイプ:type/kind/sort
損するタイプってことかよ
No.
ううん:no|er, well, ...
ううん
びくびく:being afraid of/being fearful|trembling, ながら:while/during|while
びくびくしながら
I mean, you're shy about it,
大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play, 突っ込む[つっこむ]:to thrust (something) into (something)|to plunge into|to get involved with|
それでもみんなのこと大切にして突っ込んでくるよねってこと
but you still care about everyone
and you're willing to point things out.
ホント:truth/reality/actuality, 馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
そういうところ　ホント馬みたい
In that sense,
you really are like a horse.
Huh?
馬[うま, いま]:horse|horse racing|promoted bishop
あぁ　「馬」って…
A horse?
観察[かんさつ]:observation/survey/watching, 臆病[おくびょう]:cowardice/timidity, 裏返し[うらがえし]:inside out/upside down|flip side
人をよく観察するっていうのは臆病の裏返し
Their shy nature also explains
why they're observant of people.
草食[そうしょく]:herbivorous/plant-eating/graminivorous, 動物[どうぶつ]:animal, 基本[きほん]:foundation/basis/standard, 群れ[むれ]:group/crowd/flock, 大切[たいせつ, たいせち]:important|beloved|careful, 大切[おおぎり]:large cut (e.g. of meat)|last piece of the day's programme/last act of a play
草食動物だから　基本群れを大切にする
They're herbivores,
so they value the herd.
臆病[おくびょう]:cowardice/timidity, 繊細[せんさい]:dainty/delicate (e.g. fingers)|sensitive, 思い[おもい]:thought|imagination|desire||, 動物[どうぶつ]:animal
臆病で繊細で　仲間思いの動物なの
They're shy, delicate,
and care about their kind.
They kind of sound like
a lot of trouble.
めんどくさい:bothersome/tiresome/bother to do, 生き物[いきもの]:living thing/animal
何か　めんどくさそうな生き物だな
But isn't that what's
also good about them?
めんどくさい:bothersome/tiresome/bother to do, いっしょ:together|at the same time, いっしょ:one letter/one book
そのめんどくささがまたいいっしょ？
Good about them...
ってことは　つまり
Wait, so that means...
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead
そういうことですか？　御影さん
Is that what it means, Mikage-san?
Good about them...
Mikage-san?!
御影[ごえい, みえい]:image (esp. of a deity, buddha, royal, noble, etc.), 御影[みかげ]:divine spirit/spirit of the dead
御影さん？
御影さーん！
Mikage-san, I...
俺！　俺！
I...
じぃ～
Stare.
父さん[とうさん]:father/dad/papa, おかえり:return|welcome home
あっ　父さん　おかえり
Oh, welcome back, Dad!
宿題[しゅくだい]:homework, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
もう宿題終わらせたか？
Did you finish your summer homework?
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, 週間[しゅうかん]:weeks (period of), ちょい:heirship, ちょい:just a minute/short time|somewhat
夏休みあと１週間ちょいだろ
You've only got a week
or so left of break.
うーん:hmm/well
うーん　あとちょっと…かな
Almost done, I think.
Huh?!
勉強[べんきょう]:study|diligence|discount, 身が入る[みがはいる]:to make one's best effort/to be enthused/to put your back into it, 訳[わけ]:conclusion from reasoning, judgement or calculation based on something read or heard/reason/cause, 訳[やく]:translation/version (e.g. "English version"), でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
あぁ？　勉強に身が入らん訳でもあるのか？
Is there a reason why you
can't focus on your studies?!
Right, I guess
summer's already half over.
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, 半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
そっか　もう夏休みも半分以上終わっちゃったんだ
Once the break ends,
Pork Bowl will become bacon...
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, 明ける[あける]:to open (a door, etc.)|to open (for business, etc.)|to empty||, 豚丼[ぶたどん, とんどん]:rice covered with pork and vegetables, ベーコン:bacon
夏休みが明けたら　豚丼はベーコンになっちゃうんだな
たまに:occasionally/once in a while, 手紙[てがみ]:letter, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
たまには手紙を書いてみようよ
ポストカード:postcard, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
どっかにポストカードでもあったけ
懐かしい[なつかしい]:dear/desired/missed, 顔[かお, がん]:face|look|honor|, 顔[かんばせ]:countenance/visage|face
懐かしい顔に見けて
ほんの:mere/only/just, 数[しばしば]:often/again and again/frequently, 数[かず]:number/amount, 行[ぎょう]:line (i.e. of text)|carya (austerities)|samskara (formations)|, 行[こう]:going|type of classical Chinese verse (usu. an epic)|district (of similar merchants)|, ノスタルジー:nostalgia
ほんの数行ノスタルジーを
調子[ちょうし]:tune|vein|condition||
調子はどうですか
忙しい[いそがしい, せわしい]:busy/occupied|restless, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
忙しくしていますか
無我夢中[むがむちゅう]:being absorbed in/losing oneself in, 探しまわる[さがしまわる]:to search about for/to hunt around for/to look high and low for
無我夢中で探しまわってた
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 具合[ぐあい]:condition/state/manner, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.)
あの夢の具合はどんなだい
気分転換[きぶんてんかん]:change of pace/change of mood/(mental) break (e.g. going for a walk), くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
気分転換くらいのノリで
一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same, 歌う[うたう]:to sing|to sing (one's praises in a poem, etc.)/to compose a poem
一緒に歌わないか
無我夢中[むがむちゅう]:being absorbed in/losing oneself in, 探しまわる[さがしまわる]:to search about for/to hunt around for/to look high and low for
そして無我夢中で探しまわってた
夢[ゆめ]:dream, 続き[つづき]:sequel/continuation/(also suffix) continuation (in time and space), 語り合う[かたりあう]:to talk together
あの夢の続きを語り合おうよ
明日[あした, あす]:tomorrow|near future, 頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
明日は頑張ろうぜ
未来[みらい]:the future (usually distant)|future tense|the world to come
今はそこにある未来へ
駆け出す[かけだす]:to run off/to break into a run/to start running
駆け出して さぁ 行こう
This story is a work of fiction.
The people and groups are fictitious, but the themes relating to food and life are firmly based in reality. Visiting the places and facilities used as models can be dangerous and may result it contracting diseases from the animals. Please enjoy this story as a work of fiction.